foreign
[Music]
for me to be part of your program today
and I I thank everybody that's joined
this call I've got about 30 minutes
today to make my case for Behavioral
insurance
now if you are currently doing
individual insurance sales with Manulife
and are in contact with one of our
wholesalers and you've probably heard
them
say something like Manulife is all in on
behavioral insurance and what we mean
when we say that is that we're basically
trying to transition from Simply being a
product provider and choosing to compete
and differentiate ourselves through our
focus on health and more specifically
behavioral insurance and one of the
reasons that we're doing this is that
it's our view that increasingly this is
how insurance is being sold around the
world and that's why almost seven years
ago now we chose to partner with the
Vitality group who are basically
recognized as the Undisputed leader in
the behavioral Assurance space and they
helped us bring our Vitality program to
the Canadian market so what I'd like to
do is basically share with you a little
bit about our Global Experience
with vitality
so what we're looking at here is uh
basically just a view of all of the
countries that the Vitality group has a
presence in where they have Insurance
Partners and they're operating in 40
countries worldwide they've been helping
people live longer healthier lives for
over 30 years and they currently have 30
million members
150 program partners and they're
actually seeing over a hundred million
activities logged by their members every
month
and they're also seeing a hundred
thousand new wearable devices linked uh
to the program every month so that
members can track their activity so we
think we've really chosen the right
partner to help us be the market leader
with behavioral Insurance in Canada
now you might be wondering if it's
working and I don't typically like to
use stats from outside of our Market but
as you'll see in just a second uh the
life expectancy story in South Africa is
very very compelling
first off the average life expectancy in
South Africa is 63 and of course that's
driven by poverty the AIDS uh pandemic
uh several years ago uh but much lower
than the average life expectancy would
be in Canada now when we moved to the
insurance population you can see that
the average life expectancy improves a
little bit but when we actually look at
a Vitality member you can see that it's
significantly higher uh up to age 85 and
then finally if we look at members that
are fully participating in the Vitality
program doing all the things they need
to do to improve their their health and
and making good lifestyle choices the
average life expectancy is 80 seven so I
just share that with you to basically
make the point that uh Vitality is
saving lives uh and this is particularly
true in in South Africa but it's also
true uh around the world
so how does this transition to
Behavioral or to behavioral Insurance
align with manulife's core values and
our mission uh you've probably heard us
say before that our mission is to make
decisions easier in lives better we
fundamentally believe that we should be
helping our customers we have longer
healthier and better lives and
underlying that is a few other beliefs
that we have and one is that longevity
to an unprecedented extent can be
heavily influenced by the everyday
choices that we make we also believe
that the life insurance Industries in an
incredibly unique and Powerful position
to help our customers live longer
healthier lives and when I say that what
I mean is is we typically have very long
relationships with our individual
insurance clients 20 30 40 years maybe
even and longer and so that gives us a
time frame where with the proper uh
program in place we feel like we can
influence our customers to make better
decisions we also think that there's a
tremendous opportunity to revitalize a
product category that's as critical as
ever for consumers but it's uh risk
losing some relevance to them and what I
mean by that is that traditional
Insurance typically only provides real
value at claim time where the Vitality
integrated policy is a policy that
provides real value to our customers
while they're alive so those
three things underlying our mission
there is the perspective that led us to
launch Vitality in the first place so
the next point I want to make and
question I want to answer is so why does
it work it works because it's a perfect
example of shared value at work and
shared value if you're not familiar with
that concept is a concept that was
popularized by Michael Porter out of the
Harvard Business School
so shared value basically happens when
companies address social problems as
well as they're driving their business
objectives at the same time and we
consider Insurance to be the ultimate
shared value industry
when our customers take steps to live
longer healthier lives it's obviously
good for them and it's good for their
families but it's also good for society
and it's good for the insurers so that's
shared value insurance and The Virtuous
cycle that you see on the screen and the
basic mechanics of it is is really quite
simple
when our policyholder experiences better
we pay fewer claims or we at least defer
paying claims which creates better
Financial outcomes for the company but
we take a big chunk of that value and we
plow it back into the next stage of this
virtuous cycle to create the incentives
and rewards that keep our customers
motivated this program only works if our
customers are making
longer term uh healthier choices and and
healthier lifestyle choices as well so
it's good for us it's good for our
clients it's good for society but it's
also good for advisors
customer satisfaction increases we've
got lots of evidence of just how
satisfied our Vitality clients are
compared to our non-vitality clients
we've got advisors telling us
continually that they're getting
unsolicited referrals from their
Vitality clients and we know it drives
better persistency and I'll share a few
details on this in a few minutes
so what I want to do is I want to spend
some time talking about uh why advisors
are recommending Vitality Plus
last fall we introduced two versions of
the Vitality program
for the first time we introduced we
introduced Vitality go which is a free
version of the program available to all
eligible clients and quite simply an
eligible client is the client that's 18
years of age or older and they're
purchasing a single life policy and we
also brought out Vitality plus which is
essentially an enhanced version of our
existing program
we also at the same time we added the
Vitality program to our Manulife ul and
our Manulife par products and we
actually enhanced our rewards uh partner
network with a few new reward Partners
so this was all done last fall as part
of our go big project if you will uh
something that we are referring to as
Vitality for all now ever since we did
that I've been sending spending quite a
bit of time
focused on gaining a better
understanding of why advisors are
choosing to recommend Vitality plus I
mean they don't have to right they could
simply sell one of those products and uh
the Vitality goal would be part of that
solution but uh they're making a
conscious decision to talk to their
clients about Vitality plus so I gained
a much better understanding of why they
were doing that and I thought it made
sense to try to categorize uh the
responses that I got into three
different buckets and so what I want to
do with the balance of my presentation
is to spend some time talking about
those three buckets and providing some
evidence of of what I mean by that
so the three buckets are the potential
impact that client participation in the
program can have on policy performance
and this then becomes the lead story for
the advisor whether it's the premium
savings or the potential gains in death
benefit and cash value when we're
talking about Manulife part uh you know
they present a very compelling story
but other advisors are motivated uh to
recommend Vitality because plus because
they understand through their clients or
may have experienced themselves the real
value that the rewards can offer the
potential is there to gain more
financial value from participating in
the program in many cases than what the
clients are paying for the insurance
itself and again I'll build on this uh
in a little bit more detail in a few
minutes and then the third bucket
something I'm referring to is just
driving Better Business outcomes there
was a group of advisors that have been
selling Vitality for a while and they've
just got first-hand experience at how it
drives better business outcomes for them
whether it's again more satisfied
clients receiving those unsolicited
referrals lower laps experience on their
term block just to name a few of those
Better Business outcomes so the next
several slides that I'm going to show
you are just going to take a deeper dive
into each one of these three different
buckets so the first one that I'm going
to talk about is the impact on policy
performance
and when we start talking about that we
basically uh have to look at it whether
it's a term insurance policy uh with
Vitality plus whether it's Manulife UL
or Manulife par and the impact on the
policy performance might be slightly
different with each of these products
for family term and vitality plus
there's upfront premium savings 10
percent uh for our clients but The
Upfront cost of insurance discount can
also improve manulife's competitive
position uh which is going to make it
easier for advisors to choose Manulife
for manual if you will the they also get
the 10 upfront cost of insurance savings
and obviously that can be quite
significant because we're now talking
about our permanent insurance policy
where the premiums are much larger
and because it's a flexible product
clients can actually make additional
deposits into their policy and the
potential is there to grow account
values even larger based on how engaged
they get in to the program and what
Vitality status they achieve
I don't think that we could ignore the
fact that some clients are going to
respond very favorably also to having
more control over what they pay for
their insurance based on their
participation in the program and that
idea that concept of consumers having
control over what they pay when we did
Consumer Testing that was the number one
thing that they uh valued with respect
to the Vitality program is is basically
being able to influence what they pay
for their insurance simply through again
the healthy choices they're making and
how much they participate in the program
with uh Manulife par clients have the
opportunity to positively impact their
longer term account values we don't
provide an upfront discount what we do
provide is an enhanced dividend and I'll
talk a little bit more about this in a
second
so I'm going to uh in the interest of
time basically talk about
ul and Par okay and to do that I'm going
to start with ul and I'm just going to
present a little bit of a a case study
if you will so what we're dealing with
is a male age 50 who's a non-smoker
non-smoker excuse me purchasing two and
a half million of coverage it's a phase
plus policy uh level cost of insurance
to age 100. now a couple of assumptions
is that during the payment period the
client is going to achieve a specified
Vitality status for the first 20 years
and then bronze status after that and if
you're not familiar with the program
bronze status essentially means they're
not engaging in the program
uh we're going to uh because it's
Vitality plus there is a six dollar a
month or 72 dollars a year Vitality
charge basically the cost of membership
in this case study the client's going to
pay the minimum required payment and the
discount on the COI charges is going to
be based on their achieved Vitality
status now I just have uh two screens to
show you first let's make an assumption
that this client uh is bronze okay so in
other words they receive the initial
upfront discount but they may not even
register their policy right they may not
engage in the policy and I sometimes
refer to this as the worst case scenario
but if you look at the screen you can
see that the minimum annual deposit for
uh Manulife UL without the Vitality
discount is thirty four thousand six
hundred ninety eight dollars but because
they're choosing Vitality plus with that
10 percent upfront discount that minimum
annual deposit drops to Thirty one
thousand three hundred and two dollars
but all of a sudden in year two they
don't engage in the program so they lose
that discount and they go back to
basically paying the same cost that a
client would pay for Manulife UL without
Vitality plus the 72 dollars
but the real takeaway from this slide is
that in this worst case scenario because
The Upfront savings were so significant
they continue to actually be ahead if
you will be in the green be ahead of the
game uh as you can see even after 20
years they're still in the green by
almost two thousand dollars and if we go
right out to age 85 they're still in the
green so the takeaway is in the absolute
worst case scenario
there's still ahead so the question that
I have to ask is why wouldn't you show
this right there is absolutely no
downside and I emphasize again that this
is the absolute worst case scenario but
why don't we take a look at what happens
to a client that actually
participates in the program they achieve
gold Vitality status every year for the
first 20 years now again looking at this
visual you can see that they get the 10
upfront discount just like they did with
on the previous screen
but you're also seeing that because they
are uh participating in the program they
basically maintain their discount when
you achieve gold Vitality status and
maintain your discount and they do that
for uh each of the first 20 years if you
go to the far right hand column
basically what you can see is if you
look at the end of 10 years there have
cumulative Savings of almost thirty four
thousand dollars and go out to the end
of 20 years uh
almost doubled to 67 000 almost 68 000
now again at the end of 20 years they
stop participating in the program they
achieve bronze status but even at age 85
they've almost maintained that same
cumulative savings that they achieved at
um
the end of 20 years so I'm just trying
to show you that in this particular
bucket where advisors are
positioning the product with their
clients and their focus their story is
that compelling story around uh savings
the potential for premium savings and
control over what uh the client's paying
for their insurance costs
um it does make a very compelling story
if we go to
a Manulife power scenario
basically what we're talking about here
is what happens to uh the death benefit
and the cash value when clients engage
in the program and they earn a higher
Vitality status what are the possible
outcomes
so maximum participation if you take a
look at that line that's essentially uh
about 110 percent uh Improvement in
death benefit and cash value
zero participation there's no downside
zero participation is essentially uh the
same performance as a Manulife power
without vitality and I will sometimes
have advisors tell me that you know it
seems a bit unreasonable to expect that
clients would uh Stay Gold for 20 years
my comeback to them is it's just as
unreasonable to expect that they're not
going to engage in the program and that
there won't be any Improvement in the
long-term values
the real truth is that it's somewhere in
between right depending on
uh just how engaged the client gets in
the program but again virtually no
downside and they have the ability to
impact uh their long-term account values
so that's
finishes the first bucket now I want to
talk about
how rewards offer real value now
when I talk to advisors that like to
talk about the rewards they typically do
that because of direct feedback they've
received from their clients and they
turn that feedback into storytelling if
you will where they share their clients
positive experience with new clients and
Prospects so what am I getting at here
first thing I want to mention to you is
that these rewards are totally in
addition to the policy enhancements that
we already looked at these clients are
also receiving The Upfront discount and
the opportunity to improve longer term
values
but Vitality isn't a Rewards program
I've heard that said several times and I
just want to emphasize that it's a
wellness program not a Rewards program
the rewards are simply there to provide
the incentives and the benefits for our
clients to stay engaged now when we
start talking about the rewards
uh there are there are several of them I
mean I don't have time today to go into
a lot of detail but we do provide a free
annual Health assessment through our
partnership with exam one we provide
discounts on travel and vacation
accommodations through our partnership
with Expedia
discounts on healthy apparel we've got a
relationship with Saucony
discounts on wearables whether it be
apple Garmin or Fitbit we have a robust
Apple Watch program we also provide a
choice of a free Garmin or a Fitbit
Fitness tracker to all our members up
front we've got a healthy food partner
with hello fresh
we provide a discount on gym membership
through our partnership with good life
and gamification features where every
month and or weekly clients have the
opportunity to earn gift cards or maybe
Vitality points and there's even more to
it but I just want to kind of give you
that that overview
and when I look at the rewards they kind
of fall into three different buckets
again if you if you will there's sign up
rewards these rewards are available uh
to all of our members simply for
registering their policy completing
their 20-minute Vitality Health
assessment uh at the at the beginning of
their Vitality Journey then there's
engagement rewards uh where part of the
Apple Watch program uh is based on
engagement in the program as well as the
gift cards that I talked about and then
finally there's a several rewards that
are driven by a member's Vitality status
now I don't expect you to uh
analyze these numbers and we don't have
time to go through them but what I've
tried to do here is just provide real
examples of the kind of value that
clients might achieve through uh their
engagement in the program at the various
status levels and what's really
interesting is even for clients that
don't actively participate in the
program because of those startup uh
rewards they can actually if you total
those up I'll do it for you it's over
500 of value if we in the interest of
time just go over to gold and platinum
if you totaled up those the value of
those rewards for gold it's over eleven
hundred dollars and for platinum it's
over 1800 almost 1900 in value now the
reason I share this with you is just to
demonstrate that again for some advisors
they've got some very compelling stories
from their clients about how they've
participated in the program and how
they've enjoyed the rewards
um and in many cases as you might have
heard me say earlier these rewards can
add up to more than what the clients are
actually paying for their insurance
costs
so uh now I did that the old-fashioned
manual way but we actually have a
calculator that's available on our
public site it's also available on our
advisor portal and it's really really
cool it's really simple to use and
advisors use it in a couple of different
ways they might use it in the initial
sales conversation to just demonstrate
to a prospect how easy it is to achieve
a higher Vitality status there's a eight
question eight question questionnaire
built in client answers those questions
and they basically can determine what
Vitality status they are and then from
there they can actually look at all the
various rewards based on their status
and get some idea of how much value they
could extract from the program so it's a
great way to help reinforce the sale and
it's a great way even on policy delivery
free to do the same so I just wanted to
share with you that that tool is
available so I'm going to have to move
quite quickly here in the interest of
time but that third bucket was the fact
that
selling Vitality plus can drive better
business outcomes we surveyed
advisors that were basically quite
familiar with Vitality it's it was part
of uh you know routine recommendations
that they're making to their clients and
you can see some responses that we
received from that group 75 of them said
that Vitality provides
them with new opportunities to engage
with their clients and it absolutely
does because whether it's a client
achieving a higher Vitality status
whether it's them ordering a wearable
enjoying one of the rewards there's
ample opportunities for clients and
advisors to connect and talk about that
experience and oftentimes out of that
comes other cross-sell upsell
opportunities
66 percent of the advisors we talked to
said that they appreciated the fact that
recommending Vitality provided a point
of differentiation there's nobody else
selling this kind of a robust behavioral
based uh recommendation in the
marketplace so they really appreciated
that 63 percent said that it helped them
to grow their practice by reaching new
markets and for many of our advisors
what that meant was is they a lot of
them had stopped dealing with really
younger clients the children of their uh
older clients for example but the
Vitality program just sort of brought
this whole New Perspective to talking
about insurance and it has a lot of
appeal to younger clients so it opened
up new markets for them and then finally
55 said that it was making it easier for
them to have upsell cross-sell
conversations with their clients
we've looked at our business since
um
2016. so almost seven years worth of
experience and what we've found out is
that Vitality elected policies have a 22
percent higher face amount that are
non-vitality elected policies
they're 50 percent more likely to own a
critical illness insurance policy which
I thought was really really interesting
when we looked at our term block over
that same period we had a 50 percent
lower lapse rate for our Vitality uh
policies versus non-fitality term
policies and we also found out that uh
the clients that we surveyed said that
they were 23 percent more likely to
recommend their advisor through
providing unsolicited referrals so just
to close things off I don't think we
should lose sight of the fact that
improvements in our clients health is
what this program is really all about
I've talked about premium savings I've
talked about rewards I've talked about
good business outcomes for advisors but
at the base of the program is the fact
that our clients are changing their
behavior and they're seeing significant
improvements in their health just if you
go to the bottom of the Box on the right
hand side of the screen
when our clients do that free Vitality
health check through exam one those are
verified results those results are sent
straight to Vitality our clients can
earn points for it but what we've seen
is they've gone from uh not qualifying
for the for the points because their
readings weren't in a healthy range to
where they were in a healthy range you
can see 20 percent reduce their BMI into
a healthy Range 32 percent improve their
cholesterol
56 percent improve their blood pressure
and 85 percent reported in-range glucose
readings these are the four biometric
tests that we
perform as part of uh
that free exam one health check so
I am out of time I know it was sort of a
quick overview it didn't have anything
to do with how the program works uh how
to sell it it was more about why and I
appreciate your time if I've caught your
attention at all talk to your Manulife
wholesaler right there there uh would be
really happy to hear from you and help
you figure out exactly how the program
works and and how to talk to your
clients about it so Wendy back over to
you again thank you everybody
foreign